# Gaoxiong Zeng

## Contact

E-mail: gaoxiong.zeng@huawei.com / gzengaa@connect.ust.hk Website: https://gaoxiong.site

# **Brief Biography**

Gaoxiong Zeng (曾高雄) is a staff researcher with Network Technology Lab of Huawei. He received his Ph.D. in computer science and engineering from Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, where he worked with Prof. Kai Chen. His research areas of interest include computer networks and systems, with special focuses on data center networking and transport protocols. His work has been published on various top venues such as SIGCOMM, INFOCOM, ICNP, and ToN, etc.

## Education

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST)	Hong Kong, China
Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering	2015 - 2022
Advisor: Prof. Kai Chen.	
University of Science and Technology of China (USTC)	Hefei, China
B.E. in Electronic Engineering and Information Science	2011 - 2015

# Work Experiences

[Staff Researcher] Huawei Technologies. Shenzhen, China.	2022.02 - Present
[Research Intern] Peng Cheng Laboratory. Shenzhen, China.	2019.09 - 2020.01
[Research Intern] Huawei Technologies. Hong Kong, China.	2018.11 - 2019.01
[Research Intern] Chinese Academy of Sciences. Beijing, China.	2014.07 - 2014.08

## **Publications**

#### Conference and Workshop Publications:

- Gaoxiong Zeng, Li Chen, Bairen Yi, Kai Chen. "Cutting Tail Latency in Commodity Datacenters with Cloudburst", in Proceedings of the 41th IEEE International Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM), Virtual Event, May 2-5, 2022.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Jianxin Qiu, Yifei Yuan, Hongqiang Liu, Kai Chen. "FlashPass: Proactive Congestion Control for Shallow-buffered WAN", in Proceedings of the 29th IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), Virtual Event, November 1-5, 2021.
- Shuihai Hu, Wei Bai, Gaoxiong Zeng, Zilong Wang, Baochen Qiao, Kai Chen, Kun Tan, Yi Wang. "Aeolus:
   A Building Block for Proactive Transport in Datacenters", in Proceedings of the Annual Conference of the ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM), Virtual Event, August 10-14, 2020.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Ge Chen, Kai Chen, Dongsu Han, Yibo Zhu, Lei Cui. "Congestion Control
  for Cross-Datacenter Networks", in Proceedings of the 27th IEEE International Conference on Network
  Protocols (ICNP), Chicago, USA, October 7-10, 2019.
- Jiacheng Xia, Gaoxiong Zeng, Junxue Zhang, Weiyan Wang, Wei Bai, Junchen Jiang, Kai Chen. "Rethinking Transport Layer Design for Distributed Machine Learning", in Proceedings of the 3rd ACM Asia-Pacific Workshop on Networking (APNet), Beijing, China, August 17-18, 2019.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Ge Chen, Kai Chen, Dongsu Han, Yibo Zhu. "Combining ECN and RTT for Datacenter Transport", in Proceedings of the 1st ACM Asia-Pacific Workshop on Networking (APNet), Hong Kong SAR, China, August 3-4, 2017.

#### **Journal Publications:**

- Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Ge Chen, Kai Chen, Dongsu Han, Yibo Zhu, Lei Cui. "Congestion Control for Cross-Datacenter Networks", in IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN), 2022.
- Shuihai Hu, Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Zilong Wang, Baochen Qiao, Kai Chen, Kun Tan, Yi Wang. "Aeolus: A
  Building Block for Proactive Transport in Datacenter Networks", in IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking
  (ToN), 2021.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Shuihai Hu, Junxue Zhang, Kai Chen. "Transport Protocols for Data Center Networks: A Survey", in ICT-CAS/CCF Journal of Computer Research and Development (J-CRAD), 57(1), 2020.
- Wei Bai, Shuihai Hu, **Gaoxiong Zeng**, Kai Chen. "Data Center Flow Scheduling", in Communications of the China Computer Federation (**CCCF**), 15(4), 2019.

#### Miscellaneous:

- Gaoxiong Zeng, Li Chen, Bairen Yi, Kai Chen. "Optimizing Tail Latency in Commodity Datacenters using Forward Error Correction", in arXiv:2110.15157 [cs.NI], October 28, 2021.
- Ge Chen, Gaoxiong Zeng, Li Chen. "P4COM: In-Network Computation with Programmable Switches", in arXiv:2107.13694 [cs.NI], July 29, 2021.
- Hao Wang, Jingrong Chen, Xinchen Wan, Han Tian, Jiacheng Xia, Gaoxiong Zeng, Weiyan Wang, Kai Chen,
   Wei Bai, Junchen Jiang. "Domain-specific Communication Optimization for Distributed DNN Training", in
   arXiv:2008.08445 [cs.DC], August 16, 2020.
- Shuihai Hu, Kai Chen, Gaoxiong Zeng. "Improved Path Compression for Explicit Path Control in Production Data Centers", in Poster Session of the 13th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI), Santa Clara, USA, March 16-18, 2016.

## Selected Talks

[ICNP] FlashPass: Proactive Congestion Control for Shallow-buffered WAN. Virtual Event.	Nov. 2021
[ICNP] Congestion Control for Cross-Datacenter Networks. Chicago, USA.	Oct. 2019
[APNet] Combining ECN and RTT for Datacenter Transport. Hong Kong, China.	Aug. 2017

## **Professional Services**

[Reviewer] IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN), IEEE INFOCOM, etc.

[Review Drafter] SIGCOMM 2021, NSDI 2021, INFOCOM 2021, CoNEXT 2020, SIGCOMM 2019, etc.

# Teaching & Tutoring

[Teaching Assistant] HKUST FYP: Transport Design for Data Center Networks. Fall 2019, Spring 2020 [Teaching Assistant] HKUST COMP2611: Computer Organization. Spring 2016, Fall 2016, Spring 2017

# Honors & Awards

[Huawei] Gifted Young Award (天才少年计划).

[HKUST] Research Postgraduate Scholarship.

2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021

[USTC] Graduate of the Talent Program in Computer and Information Science and Technology.

2015

[USTC] Outstanding Student Scholarship (top 15% or top 30%).

2012, 2013, 2014

[Department of Education, Guangdong] Provincial Soong Ching Ling Scholarship.

Last updated in Mar. 2022.